Guide to the Merrill K. Bennett Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Merrill K. Bennett papers
1908-1975
SC0149
Bennett, Merrill K., 1898-1969.
2.25 Linear feet
Unpublished papers and speeches (1923-1966) on topics such as agricultural costs, wartime economy, food problems of post-war Europe, and world population problems; correspondence; newsclippings; pamphlets; mementos; and other papers relating to Bennett's travels to Hawaii (1942), Japan (1947), and Africa.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of John F. Bennett, 1976.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Director, Stanford Food Research Institute (1952-1962); executive director (1942-1951); faculty member (1922-1962). Bennett was an authority on the economics of food consumption.
Description of the Collection
Unpublished papers and speeches (1923-1966) on topics such as agricultural costs, wartime economy, food problems of post-war Europe, and world population problems; correspondence; newsclippings; pamphlets; mementos; and other papers relating to Bennett's travels to Hawaii (1942), Japan (1947), and Africa.
Access Terms
Bennett, Merrill K., 1898-1969.; Stanford University. Food Research Institute. Faculty.; Africa.; Clippings.; Food consumption.; Hawaii.; Japan.; Memorabilia.; Pamphlets; Speeches.; World War, 1939-1945 --Food question.
Collection Contents
- Papers, 1908-1975
  - List of published works, 1961
    - List of Merrill Bennett's published works, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Unpublished materials: Papers and speeches, 1923-1966
    - Various topics, including national standards of living, and domestic agricultural costs, 1923-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - One long work, "Analytical summaries of farming costs", 1923-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Various topics, including California agriculture and European wartime economy, 1923-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Speeches concerning European wartime food economy, 1923-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Speeches about wartime economy, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Various topics dealing with food problems of post-war Europe, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Papers concerned with various aspects of international food economy, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Various topics, including world population problems, and food supply, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mostly correspondence to Food Research Institute (not addressed by name) from Bennett's travels in East Africa, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Materials concerned with food economy development in East Africa and foods of the New England Indians, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American Indian and Hawaiian food economies, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous topics, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Foods of the rainy tropics": notes, charts, maps and drafts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Survival and losses of Aboriginal foods": notes, charts, maps and background materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Bennett's notes on readings and a bibliography, Undated; Two small spiral notebooks (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "About Van Niel's book…": letters between Merrill Bennett and his son John Bennett, exchanging critical comments on the book, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Travel: Hawaii, 1942
    - Correspondence from Hawaii, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hawaii in wartime: newspaper clippings, 1941 December 2-1942 January 30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Hawaii in wartime: newspaper clippings, 1942 February 1-1942 February 28 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hawaii in wartime: newspaper clippings, 1942 March 1-1942 September 20 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Hawaii in wartime: pamphlets, menus, magazine photos, and "list of rumours", kept by Bennett, circa 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Envelope containing notecards, "Names and notes on interviews", circa 1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Travel: Japan, 1947
    - Mementos, business cards from Japanese associates, itinerary, personnnel lists, ID card, correspondence and Air Raid Precautions Manual, circa 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Itinerary of Japan Trip, and passenger list of Canadian Pacific Cruise, 1964, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Dorcas Bennett from Japan, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Travel: Hawaii, 1941-1942
    - Photographs of scenery, circa 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of people: some family, most unidentified, circa 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Exhibit 1-12", circa 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Negatives, circa 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Postcards (unwritten), circa 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Travel: Japan, 1947
    - Photographs, notecards, list, circa 1947 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Photographs, circa 1947 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, circa 1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 1951, 1954 and undated
    - USDA Group photographs, Washington DC, 1951, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Cousin Ben Brown and FRI friends, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Domestic travel to Yosemite, Point Lobos, Golden Gate Park, some unidentified scenes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bennett home, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Bennett family snapshots, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Notecard file, Undated
    - Notecard file containing bibliographic citations arranged by subject area, Undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence from Dorcas Gallup, 1911-1922 and undated
    - Correspondence, 1911-1918 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1920 January-March (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1920 April-May (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1920 June-December (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1921 January-March (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1921 April-August (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1921 September-October (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1921 November-December (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1922 January-February (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1922 March-April (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1922 May-June (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Dorcas Gallup, 1917-1924
    - Correspondence, 1917 August 7-October (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1917 November 1-December 27 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1918 January 2-March 28 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1918 April 15-May 27 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1918 June 2-July 15 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1918 August 2-October 30 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1918 November 5-27 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1918 December 5-24 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1919 January 2-February 13 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1919 March 10-April 7 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1919 July 3-August 27 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1919 September 8-October 14 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1919 November 10-December 16 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1920 January 24-March 9 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1920 April 7-June 13 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1920 June 16-November 6 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1920 November 18-December 18 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1921 January-February 23 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1921 March 1-April 4 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1921 April 8-May 16 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1921 May 26-June 20 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1921 September 5-24 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1921 September 25-October 14 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1921 October 16-31 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1921 November (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1921 December 1-21 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1922 January 3-12 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1922 January 18-31 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1922 February 2-28 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1922 March 2-24 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1922 March 27-April 13 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1922 April 25-May 12 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1922 May 14-June 21 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence (to Dorcas Gallup Bennett), 1924 August 28-September 20 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence (to Dorcas Gallup Bennett), 1924 September 25-October (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Family correspondence, 1922-1968 and undated
    - MKB to Dorcas Gallup Bennett, 1939 April 12-May (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - MKB to DGB, 1944 March 18-1945 January 12 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - MKB to DGB (carbon of typed transcript), 1951 May 2-23 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - MKB to DGB (carbon of typed transcript), 1951 April (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - MKB to DGB (carbon of typed transcript), 1951 March 5-27 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - MKB to DGB, 1951 February 27-May 23 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - John Gallup to MKB/DGB, 1922 September 3-1926 December 23 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - John Gallup to MKB/DGB, 1927 January 3-1928 August 7 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - John Gallup to MKB/DGB, 1929 March 4-December 9 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - John Gallup to MKB/DGB, 1930 January 20-1941 December 16 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence from MKB, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Postcards to MKB/DGB from Steve, John and Polly, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - MKB/DGB to John Bennett, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - John Bennett to MKB/DGB, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - John Bennett to MKB/DGB, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - John Bennett to MKB/DGB, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Steve Bennett to MKB/DGB, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Linnea Peterson to MKB/DGB, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Steve Bennett to MKB/DGB, 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Steve Bennett to MKB/DGB, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Steve Bennett to MKB/DGB, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Steve Bennett to MKB/DGB, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Bennett family, 1922 and undated
    - Postcards, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Family and home: photos and miscellaneous, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Three photos, Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Photographic portraits of Merrill K. Bennett, Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Western States postcard: blank, Undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Wedding announcement, 1922, Christmas cards, photos of MKB and family, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Ledgers, 1932-1974
    - Ledgers, 1932 October-1938 January (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Ledgers, 1938 January-1942 September (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Ledgers, 1942 September-1950 June (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Ledgers, 1951 August-1956 August (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Ledgers, 1956 January-1963 December (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Ledgers, 1964 January-1974 April (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Assets, budgets, bank notes, etc., Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous and oversize materials, 1939-1954 and undated
    - Miscellaneous and oversize materials, 1939-1954 and undated (Box 14)
      "2/3 Mankind Hungry too Pessimistic, Expert Says", Science service article, 1954 May 24; 2 boxes of slides: 257 total - family, 1953; domestic travel to california, Oregon, Colorado, and Texas (1951-52); Mexico; and African trip; Mementos from Japan; Postcard from Dorcas Bennett to son John, 1939 April 6; One large framed group Photograph (including Bennett) in the "House of Shining Waters", Japan; Two diplomas: M.A. Brown university, M.A. Harvard; Two testimonial scrolls: FRI retirement and recognition of service in the Governmental Food Agency; One unidentified photograph
  - Miscellaneous Memorabilia, 1908-1970 and undated
    - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1908-1964 and undated (Box 15)
      Brown Commencement Week, 1920: booklet; Japan Tour, 1964: 2 photographs; Correspondence from Australia, 1964; Sachet of slides; MKB diary 1908; 3" reel of recording tape; Dorcas B. Gallup diaries 1916, 1917, 1918; Postcards from MKB to family, miscellaneous; Miscellaneous envelopes
    - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1917-1970 and undated (Box 16)
      Brown University Handbook, 1917-1918; Address book; Notebook; 2 world maps; "Aspects of the Pig"; Dedication of Food Research Institute, 1970 April 6: program and addresses; Miscellaneous letters to MKB and Clippings
  - Miscellaneous and Biographical Materials, 1913-1975 and undated
    - Eulogy for Dorcas Gallup Bennett, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - MKB and chilldren to Dorcas Bennett, 1939 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence to MKB, 1941-1945 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Gallup family to MKB/DGB, 1927-1931 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Killingsley High School graduation program, 1913 June (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Stanford University diploma: Ph.D., 1927 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Brown University diploma: L.H.D. (honorary) and commencement program, 1954, 1921 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Certificates: birth, marriage, honorable discharge, identification papers, Undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Publications, Undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Bibliography of MKB biography, 1961 February 6 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence (re: Stanford University Oregon offer), 1920 January 15-1926 August 14 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1956-1963 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Brown University honorary degree, photos, 1954 June (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Brown University commencement attendance, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - MKB correspondence to Mrs. Blyth, circa 1919 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Materials re: MKB's death, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous from correspondence, Undated (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Newsclippings, Undated (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Saturday Morning Club, 17th anniversary, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 20)